Guide to the Common Sense Foundation Records, 1983-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Common Sense Foundation records 1983-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Common Sense Foundation.
19.0 linear feet Extent: Approximately 11,625 Items
Progressive policy think-tank based in North Carolina. Spanning the years 1983 to 2008, the Common Sense Foundation (CSF) Records contain manuscript, print, audiovisual, and electronic materials related to the foundation's administration and work on various policy initiatives, which include the death penalty, taxation and economic justice, the environment, gay rights, health care, testing in public schools and other education issues, the tobacco industry, and North Carolina politics. The collection primarily contains clippings, reports, administrative documents, and correspondence, including emails, and is organized into the following series: Administrative Files, Audiovisual Materials, Board of Directors, Photographs, Printed Materials, Research Files, Staff Files, and Website. The largest group of materials relates to CSF's research on public policy. Several thousand electronic files in the collection have been migrated to a library server. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
RL.00249
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Some materials in the collection are closed. The Board of Director Series is closed until June 8, 2020.
Electronic records have been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection. Files must be screened for confidential material before use can be granted.
Also, original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Common Sense Foundation Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010.
Historical Note
The Common Sense Foundation (CSF) was a progressive, nonprofit, public-policy organization incorporated in Raleigh, North Carolina in 1994. It sought to promote "fairness, justice, and opportunity in the state public-policy debate." Executive Director Chris Fitzsimon led CSF from 1994-2003. Among CSF's publications were the Journal of Common Sense from 1995 to 2001 and Common Sense Says... from 1998 to 2007. In 1997, CSF began offering a weekly email update, called the Common Sense Legislative Update, with a subscription base of over 500 people. CSF launched its website in 1998. Its primary policy initiatives included the death penalty and testing in public schools. In 2003, Research Director David Mills took over for Chris Fitzsimon as CSF's Executive Director. At its height, CSF had a membership of approximately 800 and a permanent staff of four. CSF dissolved in 2008.
Collection Overview
Spanning the years 1983 to 2008, the Common Sense Foundation Records contain manuscript, print, audiovisual, and electronic materials related to CSF's administration and work on various policy initiatives, which include the death penalty, taxation and economic justice, the environment, gay rights, health care, testing in public schools and other education issues, health care, the tobacco industry, and North Carolina politics, and many other civil rights issues. The collection primarily contains clippings, reports, administrative documents, and correspondence, including emails, and is organized into the following series: Administrative Files, Audiovisual Materials, Board of Directors, Photographs, Printed Materials, Research Files, Staff Files, and Website. The largest group of materials relates to CSF's research on public policy. Thousands of electronic files representing materials related to the series in the collection have been migrated to a library server. Files must be screened for confidential material before use can be granted.
Several series focus on the administration of the foundation. In addition to documenting the foundation's bylaws and history, the Administrative Files Series contains documents related to CSF's finances and membership, sponsorship of events, strategic planning, and personnel. Related material can also be found in the Staff Files Series. The administration and strategic plan of the foundation is also treated in the Board of Directors Series (closed until 2020), which contains minutes of board meetings and information about board members. The Photographs Series houses images of CSF events.
Other series document the foundation's policy initiatives. The Printed Materials Subseries contains copies of works published by CSF, clippings of articles written by CSF staff, and publications on related topics printed by other organizations. Organized by topic, the Research Files Series contains files related to the foundation's research and organizing work, principally on the death penalty, economic issues, fair testing in public schools, North Carolina politicians, and health care. Primarily containing clippings and reports, this series also includes letters written by incarcerated people to CSF, and includes the foundation's survey of lawyers who represented death row inmates. The Audiovisual Materials Series contains videocassettes related to CSF's policy initiatives and that document foundation-sponsored events. CSF's presence on the internet is documented in the Website Series, which contains both policy and administrative material.
Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Subject Headings
Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Common Sense Foundation; North Carolina. General Assembly; Capital punishment -- North Carolina; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- North Carolina; Environmental policy -- North Carolina; Education -- North Carolina; Educational tests and measurements -- Law and legislation -- North Carolina; Gay rights; Human rights -- North Carolina; Public health -- North Carolina; Sexual minorities -- North Carolina; Taxation -- North Carolina; Tobacco industry -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Economic conditions; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Machine-readable records; Videocassettes
Separated Material
The following printed volumes were separated from the collection:
Kelly, Charles M. The Great Limbaugh Con and Other Right-Wing Assaults on Common Sense, Santa Barbara, CA: Fithian Press, 1994.
Moore, L. Edward. Getting Greener: Progressive Environmental Ideas for the American South, Charleston: Center for a Better South, 2007.
North Carolina Council of Community Programs. Directory of North Carolina Area Mental Health, Developmental Disabilities, Substance Abuse Programs, 2002.
North Carolina State Bar. North Carolina Legal Directory, Dallas: Legal Directories Publishing Company: 2003.
Center for Policy Alternatives. Progressive Agenda for the States 2006, Washington, DC: Center for Policy Alternatives, 2006.
Contents of Collection
- Administrative Files Series, 1994-2008, (9 boxes and 3234 electronic files)
  Contains electronic and paper files concerning the general operations of the foundation. Arranged into subseries on Fundraising and Membership, Events and Projects, Meetings and Planning, Personnel, and Other documents. Some related documents can also be found in the Staff Files Series.
  - Events and Projects Subseries, 1995-2008
    Contains electronic and paper files related to projects and events sponsored by the foundation. Events include invited speakers, meetings with legislators, house parties to promote membership and/or particular causes, and Message Madness, a grassroots training program for activists and non-profits. Other materials relate to CSF's participation in the Peace List Enhancement Action Project (LEAP) and the North Carolina Alliance for Economic Justice (NCAEJ). Documents include mailings, handouts, attendance lists, and planning materials. Folders are arranged by topic and then chronologically.
    [Electronic records have been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection. Files must be screened for confidential material before use can be granted.]
    - Guest register for An Uncommon Evening, 1995 Nov 4 (Box 1)
    - Events, 1997-2003, (24 folders) (Box 1)
    - Legislative web project, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Message Madness, 1997-2007, (11 of 17 folders) (Box 1)
    - Message Madness, 1997-2007, (6 of 17 folders) (Box 2)
      Separated Material
      Two CD-Roms have been removed from the folder labeled 2006 Message Madness
      [Records have been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection. Files must be screened for confidential material before use can be granted.]
    - North Carolina Alliance for Economic Justice, 2002-2003, (5 folders) (Box 2)
    - Peace LEAP, 2001-2007, (6 folders) (Box 2)
    - Electronic files, 1998-2008 (Box 2)
      - Calendars, (3 folders, 15 files, 523 KB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 2)
      - Special Events, (22 folders, 125 files, 9.26 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 2)
      - Message Madness, (6 folders, 67 files, 2.40 MB) (Efolder Message Madness, Box 2)
  - Fundraising and Membership Subseries, 1996-2008 (Box 2)
    Contains electronic and paper files related to the foundation's finances and membership. Documents include budgets, donor and member lists, and grant applications. Folders are arranged by topic and then chronologically.
    - Donor and member lists and mailings, 2000-2002, (12 of 32 folders) (Box 2)
    - Donor and member lists and mailings, 2000-2002, (20 of 32 folders) (Box 3)
    - Grant applications, 1996-2008, (10 of 24 folders) (Box 3)
    - Grant applications, 1996-2008, (14 of 24 folders) (Box 4)
      One CD-Rom has been removed from the folder labeled Case 99-384.
    - Electronic files, 2001-2008 (Box 4)
      - Database, (3 folders, 45 files, 209 MB) (Efolder Database, Box 4)
      - Accounting and Finances, (20 folders, 118 files, 16.5 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 4)
      - CES DataBase, (6 files, 19.8 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 4)
      - Donors, (2 folders, 10 files, 838 KB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 4)
      - Foundation Foundations, (3 files, 74.5 KB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 4)
      - Grant Research, (5 files, 139 KB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 4)
      - Insurance, (5 files, 718 KB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 4)
      - Invoices, (16 files, 473 KB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 4)
      - Proposals, (10 folders, 50 files, 1.68 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 4)
      - Thank You, (15 files, 2.83 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 4)
      - Monthly Renewals, (7 folders, 68 files, 2.09 MB) (Efolder Monthly Renewals, Box 4)
      - Sales Tax Refund, (5 files, 439 KB) (Efolder Sales Tax Refund, Box 4)
  - Meetings and Planning Subseries, 2000-2003 (Box 4)
    Contains electronic and paper files produced during staff meetings and retreats as well as those related to the foundation's mission and strategic plan. Folders are arranged by topic and then chronologically.
    - Staff meetings and retreats, 2000-2003, (10 folders) (Box 4)
    - Strategic planning, 2000-2001, (17 folders) (Box 4)
    - Electronic files, 2000 (Box 4)
      - StratPlan 2000, (8 folders, 47 files, 2.03 MB) (Efolder StratPlan 2000, Box 4)
  - Other Documents Subseries, 1994-2008 (Box 4)
    Contains miscellaneous administrative electronic and paper files. Folders are arranged by topic and then chronologically.
    - Academic advisory committee, 1997 (Box 5)
    - Articles of incorporation, 1994, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - By-laws, 2002, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Charitable solicitation license, 1999-2007, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1995-2008, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - CSF accomplishments, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Event planning, 2002, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Instructions for technology and mailings, 2000-2004, (10 folders) (Box 5)
    - Journal, 2000-2001, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Logo redesign, 2000 (Box 5)
    - Other documents, 1996-2007, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - North Carolina non-profit letter, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Office property, 2002-2007, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Resources for non-profits, 2000-2006, (9 folders) (Box 6)
    - Speeches, 1994-2005, (8 folders) (Box 6)
    - Talk shows, 1995, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Electronic files, 1998-2008 (Box 6)
      - Contact Numbers & Lists, (14 files, 1.61 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 6)
      - Faxes, (4 files, 186 KB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 6)
      - Letterheads, Coversheets, Labels, Templates, etc, (36 files, 1.20 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 6)
      - Letters, (14 files, 3.88 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 6)
      - Logos and Brochure, (17 files, 3.73 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 6)
      - Manuals, (8 files, 1.24 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 6)
      - Old Word, Access, Excel Docs, (4 folders, 37 files, 5.68 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 6)
      - Research\Academic Advisory Committee, (13 files, 506 KB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 6)
  - Personnel Subseries, 1999-2008 (Box 6)
    Contains electronic and paper files related to staff, interns, and volunteers. Documents include job descriptions, recruitment efforts, publicity, and policy manuals. Personally-identifiable personnel records and search committee materials with personal information have been removed. Folders are arranged by topic and then chronologically.
    - Personnel and staff management files, 1999-2008, (9 folders) (Box 6)
    - Electronic files, 2000-2004 (Box 6)
      - Personnel and Staff Related, (289 folders, 2,631 files, 44.5 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 6)
- Audiovisual Material Series, 1994-2007 and undated, (27 videocassettes) (Box 6)
  Contains videocassettes that document Common Sense Foundation events or are related to policy initiatives, such as the death penalty and education.
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - Communications Is What It's All About! Raleigh, NC: TMP Video Communications, 1996 (Box 7)
  - The Death Penalty Glasgow, Scotland: Media Services, undated (Box 7)
  - Effective School Partnerships: Easy as 1-2-3. Running time: 16:30. [NC]: Parent Partners, undated (Box 7)
  - Fair testing commission, Durham, 2001 May 17 (Box 7)
  - Going to the Well. Running time: 12:18. Washington DC: Advocacy Institute, undated (Box 7)
  - Health in America: Search for a Cure. Running time: 57:00. Introduction by Dr. Charles Sanders, undated (Box 7)
  - The Great Limbaugh Con. Running time: 47:50. Raleigh, NC: The Common Sense Foundation, 1994 (Box 7)
  - High stakes testing, undated (Box 7)
  - L & E Research, Inc. 5:30 pm, 2006 June 29 (Box 7)
  - L & E Research, Inc. 7:30 pm, 2006 June 29 (Box 7)
  - Legislative Week in Review, Episode 816, May 11, 2001. Produced by Mary Kannan DeMolli. Research Triangle Park, NC: UNCTV, 2001 (Box 7)
  - AT issue lottery, undated (Box 7)
  - Message Madness, undated (Box 7)
  - Media Training: Common Sense, El Pueblo, Acorn, 2006 July 11 (Box 7)
  - Media Training: Action for Children, NC Voter Ed, Common Sense, 2007 Feb. 14 (Box 7)
  - No Other Choice, undated (Box 8)
  - Predatory lending practices news coverage. Running time: 27:26, 1997-1998 (Box 8)
  - People, Pigs & Politics: Cleaning Up the Hog Industry in North Carolina. Running time: 19:00. Charlottesville, VA: Southern Environmental Law Center, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Testing forum - Charlotte, 2001 Oct. 18, (2 videocassettes) (Box 8)
  - Testing forum - Greensboro, 2001 Oct. 10 (Box 8)
  - Testing forum - Wilmington, 2001 Sept. 20 (Box 8)
  - The Unmet Promise. [NC]: Legal Services of North Carolina, Inc., undated (Box 8)
  - Unlabeled videocassettes, (4 items) (Box 8)
- Board of Directors Series, 1996-2008, (2 boxes and 270 electronic files) (Box 8)
  Contains electronic and paper files concerning the Foundation's Board of Directors, including minutes of board meetings and retreats. Arranged in original order as received.
  [Records in this series are CLOSED until June 8, 2020.]
  - Articles of incorporation (Box 9)
  - Executive committee, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Member survey (Box 9)
  - Board development committee (Box 9)
  - Bylaws, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Rebecca High (Box 9)
  - New board member info (Box 9)
  - Board bios (Box 9)
  - Board packets, (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - Board member expectations (Box 9)
  - Board labels (Box 9)
  - Board member job description (Box 9)
  - Board development (Box 9)
  - Helpful tips (Box 9)
  - Mission Statement (Box 9)
  - Board recruitment (Box 9)
  - Board fundraising (Box 9)
  - Advisory committee (Box 9)
  - Clips, 2001 (Box 9)
  - Succession planning (Box 9)
  - Meeting schedule (Box 9)
  - Board how-to (Box 9)
  - Work plan (Box 9)
  - Old board info (Box 9)
  - Budget information, (7 folders) (Box 9)
  - Board meeting minutes and notes, 1996-2008, (6 of 40 folders) (Box 9)
  - Board meeting minutes and notes 1996-2008, (34 of 40 folders) (Box 10)
  - Board retreat files, 1998-2005, (6 folders) (Box 10)
  - Electronic files, 1999-2008 (Box 10)
    - Board, (3 files 139 KB) (Efolder Alison, Box 10)
      Records are closed until June 8, 2020.
    - Board, (30 folders, 182 files, 7.30 MB) (Efolder Board, Box 10)
    - Board of Directors, (49 files, 1.72 MB) (Efolder Brian, Box 10)
    - ChrisF\CSF\Board, (36 files, 882 KB) (Efolder Former Employees, Box 10)
- Photographs Series, 2002-2006 and undated, (3 folders and 179 electronic files) (Box 10)
  Contains print and electronic photographs of foundation speakers and events, especially Message Madness.
  - Message Madness, undated, (12 prints) (Box 11)
  - 2002 Feb. 25, (22 prints) (Box 11)
  - CD-Rom (Box 11)
    One CD-Rom has been removed from this folder. [Records have been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection. Files must be screened for confidential material before use can be granted.]
  - Electronic files, 2006 and undated (Box 11)
    - My Pictures, (18 folders, 91 files, 164 MB) (Efolder Brian, Box 11)
    - CSF Pics, (88 files, 113 MB) (Efolder Brian, Box 11)
- Printed Material Series, 1983-2008, (5 boxes and 1613 electronic files) (Box 11)
  Contains a wide variety of publications in both print and electronic form. Includes reports, periodicals, flyers, and pamphlets published by the Common Sense Foundation, such as The Journal of Common Sense and Common Sense Says.... Also includes publications printed by other organizations and clippings of articles written by Chris Fitzsimon, the foundation's first director, as well as articles that mention the foundation. Materials relate to a variety of the foundation's policy initiatives, such as fair testing, the death penalty, and workers' rights. Organized into Clippings, Common Sense Foundation Publications, and Other Publications subseries, the materials are in original order as received.
  - Clippings Subseries, 1995-2003 (Box 11)
    - From The Left, Chris Fitzsimon's monthly column in the Triangle Business Journal, 1996-1999, (66 folders) (Box 11)
    - Fitzsimon's articles in The Charlotte Observer (Box 11)
    - Fitzsimon's articles in The Independent (Box 11)
    - Fitzsimon's articles in The News and Observer (Box 11)
    - Fitzsimon's articles in The Spectator, (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - Articles written by Jim Jenson (Box 11)
    - TV news clips referring to CSF (Box 11)
    - News clippings referring to CSF, 1997-2002, (33 of 45 folders) (Box 11)
    - News clippings referring to CSF, 1997-2002, (12 of 45 folders) (Box 12)
    - Electronic files, 1995-2003 (Box 12)
      - News Items, (71 folders, 1,017 files, 4.84 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 12)
  - Common Sense Foundation Publications Subseries, 1995-2007 (Box 12)
    - Common Sense Foundation Publication list, 2000, winter (Box 12)
    - Common Sense Says..., Vols. 1-10, 1998-2007, (18 folders) (Box 12)
    - Common Sense Notes, 1995-1996, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Journal of Common Sense, Vols. 1-6, 1995-, (5 of 23 folders) (Box 12)
    - Journal of Common Sense, Vols. 1-6, 1995-2001, (18 of 23 folders) (Box 13)
    - The Plain Truth, 2001-2002, 2006, (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - The State of the Worker in North Carolina, 2000 (Box 13)
    - Race and the Death Penalty, 1993-1997, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Liberty and Justice For All, a study of LGBT issues, 2005 (Box 13)
    - Common Sense Guide to the General Assembly, 1995, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Common Sense Guide to the General Assembly, 1995, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Common Sense Guide to the General Assembly, 1999-2000 (Box 14)
    - Local TV News, report,1998 (Box 14)
    - Public opinion survey, 2005 (Box 14)
    - Schools press release, 1999 (Box 14)
    - AIDs press release, 2002 (Box 14)
    - Sentencing press release, 2003 (Box 14)
    - State of the worker and death penalty postcards (Box 14)
    - Consider This flyer (Box 14)
    - Workers' rights flyers (Box 14)
    - LGBT issues and lobbying reform flyers (Box 14)
    - Fair testing flyers (Box 14)
    - Common Sense in the News flyers (Box 14)
    - Death penalty brochure (Box 14)
    - Diskettes (Box 14)
      Five 3.5" diskettes have been removed from this folder. [Records have been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
    - Electronic files, 1995-2004 (Box 14)
      - Research\CS Says, (35 folders, 188 files, 17.4 MB) (Efolder General Admin, Box 14)
      - Publications, (39 folders, 408 files, 12.9 MB) (Efolder Publications, Box 14)
  - Other Publications Subseries, 1983-2008 (Box 14)
    - The New Right in the States, 1983 (Box 14)
    - Rethinking Rural Development (Box 14)
    - Back on Track, 2006 (Box 14)
    - Conservative Citizen, 2006 Spring and Fall (Box 14)
    - Improving Your Business Climate, 1996 (Box 14)
    - Life or Death Matter, article from The Charlotte Observer, 2002 Oct. 22 (Box 14)
    - The Achievement Gap 2001: A Progress Report (Box 14)
    - How to Change Health Policies Affecting North Carolina Consumers, by Pam Silberman, J.D., Ph.D. (Box 14)
    - Mining the Golden Years, in The Independent, 1997 Apr. 30-May 6 (Box 14)
    - Public employees and testing flyers (Box 14)
    - QNotes: LGBT News and Views, 2007 Oct. 6 - Nov. 17 (Box 14)
    - QNotes: LGBT News and Views, 2007 Dec. 1 - 2008 Jan. 21 (Box 15)
    - Mental Illness and the Death Penalty, 2006 (Box 15)
    - Understanding Capital Punishment, 2003 Mar. (Box 15)
    - Not in our Name: Murder Victims' Families Speak out Against the Death Penalty, 2003 (Box 15)
    - Working Hard is Not Enough, 1997 (Box 15)
    - Bulletin of the Friends of Thomas Paine, 2006-2008 (Box 15)
    - Assorted reports and surveys, (3 folders) (Box 15)
    - Assorted other periodicals (Box 15)
    - Non-Profit periodicals (Box 15)
    - Non-profit guides (Box 15)
- Research Files Series, 1993-2008, (16 boxes and 282 electronic files) (Box 15)
  Contains electronic and paper research files related to the foundation's policy initiatives. Folders are arranged into subseries by topic and then chronologically. Some related documents can also be found in the Staff Files Series.